Hello everyone and welcome back to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎回到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And my name is Catherine and today we have an upper intermediate level lesson all about
我是Catherine，今天我们有一个中高级课程，主题是关于
money.
钱。
That's right.
没错。
We are going to be talking about money but most importantly we need to start saving money.
我们要谈谈钱，但最重要的是，我们需要开始省钱。
We need to spend less.
我们需要少花钱。
Exactly.
正是。
So, in order to control spending today we're talking about budgeting.
所以，为了控制开支，今天我们讨论预算。
So let's take a look at this very important word in today's vocabulary preview.
那么，让我们看看今天词汇预览中这个非常重要的词。
Alright, so as you mentioned, budgeting is, what is to budget?
好的，正如你提到的，预算是什么？什么是做预算？
To budget, that's the verb.
做预算，那是动词。
So budgeting is deciding how to spend your money, okay?
所以预算就是决定如何花钱，对吧？
So that means that we prepare a plan for how to spend money.
这意味着我们准备一个计划来花钱。
Alright, so that can be a noun and a verb.
好的，所以它可以是名词和动词。
A budget is the plan on how you're going to spend money and to budget is to execute this
预算就是关于如何花钱的计划，而做预算就是执行这个
plan.
计划。
Exactly.
正是。
So, today we're budgeting a family's spending.
所以，今天我们为一个家庭的支出做预算。
We're trying to control how much this family will spend in the future.
我们试图控制这个家庭未来花多少钱。
Alright, very good.
好的，非常好。
So why don't we listen to this dialogue for the first time.
那我们第一次听这段对话吧。
Welcome Mr. and Mrs. Carnwell.
欢迎Carnwell先生和太太。
Please take a seat.
请坐。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So, I understand that your family spending has skyrocketed and you want to start budgeting.
所以，我了解到你们家的开支激增了，你们想开始做预算。
Yes, that's correct.
是的，没错。
Frankly speaking, our household income is relatively high and we have never had any
坦白说，我们的家庭收入相对较高，我们从未有过任何
money problems, but I think this is the main reason as to why our spending has gone out
财务问题，但我认为这正是我们开支失控的
of control.
主要原因。
We have two kids and with allowances paying their credit cards, ours, and not to mention
我们有两个孩子，加上零花钱、支付他们的信用卡、我们的信用卡，更不用说
our mortgage and car payments.
我们的房贷和车贷了。
With the recent economic downturn, my husband's business has suffered and now we need some
最近经济不景气，我丈夫的生意受到了影响，我们现在需要一些
advice as how we can prepare a family budget.
关于如何制定家庭预算的建议。
I see.
我明白了。
Well, you have come to the right place.
嗯，你们来对地方了。
First, what we need to do is determine your cash flow.
首先，我们需要确定你们的现金流。
Knowing how much money is coming in will help us allocate spending to different categories
知道有多少钱进账，会帮助我们分配开支到不同的类别，
such as mortgage, education, groceries, etc.
比如房贷、教育、食品杂货等。
Yes, that makes sense.
是的，有道理。
Secondly, I need you to bring all of your receipts for the last two to three months.
其次，我需要你带上过去两三个月的所有收据。
That way we can determine what your average expenditures are and see which category you
这样我们就能算出你的平均支出，看看你在哪个类别上
are spending money on the most.
花钱最多。
Usually, your fixed costs are higher and we can't do much about that, but we can usually
通常，你的固定成本比较高，这方面我们无能为力，但通常我们可以
trim your variable costs such as entertainment or clothing.
削减你的可变成本，比如娱乐或服装。
Great!
太好了！
We will do that then.
那我们就这么办吧。
Now how about we treat you to a nice dinner?
现在我们请你吃顿好的晚餐怎么样？
That's another thing.
那是另一回事。
If you really want to stop spending so much money, throw away at least half of your credit
如果你真的想停止花那么多钱，那就扔掉至少一半的信用卡。
cards.
cards. 卡片。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So there were some interesting words and phrases in this dialogue related to budgeting and
这个对话里有一些和预算相关的有趣的单词和短语。
a lot of financial terms here.
这里有很多金融术语。
So let's get started now on Language Takeaway.
那么现在让我们开始进入“语言要点”环节。
Language Takeaway
语言要点
This first term is very important because it tells us what kind of a budget we're talking
第一个术语非常重要，因为它告诉我们我们讨论的是哪种预算。
about.
关于。
We're not talking about a company here.
我们这里说的不是一家公司。
We're talking about a family.
我们在谈论一个家庭。
And so in this case, we use the phrase household.
所以在这种情况下，我们使用“household”这个词。
So what are we talking about?
那我们聊什么呢？
Household income.
家庭收入。
Alright, so income we know is the amount of money that comes in to maybe your wallet,
好的，我们知道收入就是进入你钱包的钱。
my income, my personal income.
我的收入，我的个人收入。
That's how much money you earn.
这就是你赚的钱。
So a household income is how much money the house earns.
所以家庭收入就是整个家庭赚了多少钱。
So all the people that are living in this house, right?
所以住在这栋房子里的人，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
So it could be a family.
所以可能是一家人。
It could be two married people who are married to each other.
可能是两个已经结婚的人。
So the idea is that it's not one person's income.
所以，这个想法是，这不仅仅是一个人的收入。
It's the household income.
这是家庭总收入。
Think of a house.
想象一栋房子。
Alright, so it's the combined income of everyone that's living there or that's making money
好的，所以这是指所有住在那儿或赚钱的人的总收入。
that lives in this house.
住在这栋房子里的人。
Right.
好的。
So if Marco and I have a household, I earn $10,000 and he earns $10,000.
所以如果马可和我组成一个家庭，我赚一万美元，他也赚一万美元。
Our household income is $20,000.
我们家的年收入是两万美元。
Very good.
很好。
Alright.
好的。
So now we know what our household income is and in this case we have children and we give
那么现在我们知道了家庭收入是多少，在这个例子里我们有孩子，并且我们给
our kids an allowance.
孩子们零花钱。
Okay so I had an allowance when I was a kid.
好的，我小时候也有零花钱。
This is the amount of money I got from my parents every week.
这是我每周从父母那里得到的钱。
So I get I think $10 a week and I could spend it on anything I wanted and I didn't have
我每周大概得到10美元，可以花在任何我想买的东西上，而且我不需要
to work because my parents gave the money to me.
工作，因为父母直接把钱给我。
And so an allowance is this money.
所以零花钱就是这笔钱。
It's the money that mom and dad give to their children maybe every month or maybe every
这是爸爸妈妈给孩子的钱，可能是每个月，也可能是每
week.
周。
Now it's not only related to children, right?
不过这不只限于孩子，对吧？
Because maybe if you have a brother or maybe you're married and your wife is a housewife,
因为如果你有个兄弟，或者你结婚了，你妻子是家庭主妇，
maybe you give her an allowance, right?
你可能会给她零花钱，对吧？
Or the opposite.
或者反过来。
Maybe you're a house husband and you get an allowance from your wife.
也许你是家庭主夫，从妻子那里拿零花钱。
That's right.
没错。
You can have an allowance if you're anyone.
任何人都可以有零花钱。
You can also have an allowance from your company if you go traveling.
如果你出差旅行，你也可以从公司拿到零花钱。
So if you have a business trip, your company gives you a food allowance.
所以如果你有商务旅行，公司会给你餐补。
That's the amount of money you can spend on food.
那是你可以花在食物上的钱。
And you don't have to work for it.
而且你不需要为此工作。
That's the best part.
这是最棒的部分。
Awesome.
太棒了。
Alright so after these allowances, they were talking about how the economic downturn has
好的，在讨论完这些零花钱之后，他们谈到了经济衰退如何
affected their income and their spending.
影响了他们的收入和支出。
Okay so down, you think this is a negative thing.
好的，“down”这个词，你觉得这是负面的。
You're right.
你说得对。
Downturn means when a situation gets worse or slows down.
“Downturn”意思是情况变糟或放缓。
And in this case, the economy is what got worse.
在这个例子里，是经济变糟了。
And you remember this from last year.
你还记得去年的事吧。
Things started to get very difficult for people who are in business.
做生意的人开始遇到很大的困难。
And this has affected families.
这影响到了家庭。
And so we call this situation an economic downturn.
所以我们把这种情况称为经济衰退。
Now the opposite would be an economic boom.
相反的情况就是经济繁荣。
That's right.
没错。
A boom is when things are going well.
“Boom”是指情况顺利的时候。
That means people are earning more money.
这意味着人们赚更多的钱。
There are more jobs.
有更多的工作机会。
Alright.
好的。
Very good.
非常好。
Now moving on, as they were talking about budgeting, they mentioned this very important
现在继续，当他们讨论预算时，提到了一个非常重要的词。
word, very technical, is to allocate money into different areas.
这个词很专业，就是把钱分配到不同的领域。
That's right.
没错。
Allocate spending.
分配支出。
This is a verb.
这是一个动词。
To allocate.
分配。
That means to decide where the money will go.
意思是决定钱花在哪里。
Okay so as the mother in a family, I will allocate 10% of the money to the children's
好的，所以作为家里的母亲，我会把10%的钱分配给孩子们的零花钱。
allowances.
零花钱。
That's a lot.
那可真不少。
50% to the mortgage.
50%用于房贷。
20% to the car.
20%用于汽车。
Car repairs.
汽车维修。
So you're allocating your spending.
所以你是在分配你的支出。
That's right.
没错。
I'm deciding where to spend the money.
我在决定钱花在哪里。
And well, talking about spending, we have this word, expenditures.
说到支出，我们有一个词，支出。
Expenditures.
支出。
And so this is a really important word if you're in business as well because we consider
这个词在商业中也非常重要，因为当我们谈论公司赚多少钱时，会考虑支出。
expenditures when we're talking about how much a company earns.
支出是我们花钱的东西。
Expenditures are things that we spend money on.
So remember that word, expenditures.
所以记住这个词，支出。
Spend.
花。
Okay.
好的。
So an expenditure.
所以支出。
That's a noun and usually it's in the plural.
这是一个名词，通常用复数形式。
Expenditures.
支出。
Exactly.
没错。
Expenditures.
支出。
So we have many expenditures at my house.
所以我家有很多支出。
Among them, we have the car, the rent, healthcare, things like that.
其中包括汽车、房租、医疗等等。
Okay.
好的。
Perfect.
完美。
So really good phrases there.
所以这些短语非常好。
Really good vocabulary items.
词汇项目也很好。
Why don't we move on now to Fluency Builder.
我们为什么不继续到流利度训练部分呢。
Fluency Builder.
流利度训练。
We've got some very fun phrases today, Marco, in Fluency Builder.
马可，今天流利度训练里有一些很有趣的短语。
This first one is a very common phrase that we hear in songs and movies.
第一个是我们在歌曲和电影中经常听到的常见短语。
To skyrocket.
飙升。
All right.
好的。
What is skyrocket?
什么是飙升？
Well, you think about a rocket, you know, that's a ship that goes to space.
嗯，你想想火箭，就是那种飞向太空的飞船。
To skyrocket means to go up really high, really fast.
飙升的意思是快速大幅上升。
The price of gas has skyrocketed.
汽油价格飙升了。
So I remember when I was a kid, gas used to be 98 cents a gallon.
我记得我小时候，汽油每加仑98美分。
And in the 2000s, the price skyrocketed and it ended up being like $4 a gallon.
到了2000年代，价格飙升，最后涨到每加仑4美元。
Yeah, it was really expensive.
是啊，真的很贵。
All right.
好的。
So this is also, you can talk about sales have skyrocketed or the price of petroleum
所以你也可以说销售额飙升了，或者石油价格飙升了。
has skyrocketed.
飙升了。
So it could be a good thing or a bad thing, depending on what you're talking about.
所以这可能是好事也可能是坏事，取决于你在说什么。
All right.
好的。
And now moving on, they said that their spending was out of control.
现在继续，他们说他们的支出失控了。
Yeah.
是的。
So this family doesn't seem to understand how to budget.
所以这家人似乎不懂如何做预算。
They spend on everything.
他们什么都花钱。
And so the accountant says that your spending is out of control.
所以会计说你的支出失控了。
That means that you're spending too much.
意思是说你花得太多了。
There's no order to the way that you're spending.
你的花钱方式没有条理。
And we actually have a lesson, a previous lesson called out of control spending that
我们之前有一节课叫“失控的支出”，也谈到了这个话题。
we also touched this topic of what we talk about out of control.
我们讨论了什么是失控。
Something is out of control.
某件事失控了。
A person can be out of control.
一个人也可能失控。
Like a child.
比如一个孩子。
This child is out of control.
这个孩子失控了。
He never stops screaming and hitting people.
他不停地尖叫打人。
All right.
好的。
And our last phrase for today, the accountant says, well, you've come to the right place.
今天我们最后一个短语，会计说，嗯，你来对地方了。
Okay.
好的。
This is him.
这就是他。
This is the accountant bragging.
这是会计在自夸。
He's saying, well, I can fix your problems.
他在说，嗯，我能解决你的问题。
I can help you.
我能帮你。
You've come to the right place.
你来对地方了。
You can use this in many different ways.
你可以在很多不同场合用这个短语。
For example, I have a problem maybe with my TV and I say, Marco, oh my gosh, my TV doesn't
比如，我的电视可能出了问题，我说，马可，天哪，我的电视坏了。
work.
不工作了。
I don't know what to do.
我不知道该怎么办。
Can you help?
你能帮忙吗？
Right.
对。
And I can say, well, you've come to the right place.
然后我可以说，嗯，你来对地方了。
I'm an expert in my TV.
我是电视专家。
Marco's an expert in electronics.
马可是电子产品的专家。
I'm an expert.
我是专家。
All right.
好的。
So, you've come to the right place.
所以，你来对地方了。
It's a very common phrase, especially as you say when somebody's trying to brag and say,
这是一个很常见的短语，尤其是当有人想自夸时说，嗯，我知道怎么解决你的问题，或者我知道你需要什么。
well, I know how to fix your problems or I know what you need.
我擅长这个。
I'm good at this.
You've come to the right place.
你来对地方了。
If you want to learn English, you've come to the right place.
如果你想学英语，你来对地方了。
Exactly.
没错。
EnglishPod.com.
EnglishPod.com。
All right.
好的。
So, let's listen to our dialogue for the last time.
那么，让我们最后听一遍对话。
Welcome Mr. and Mrs. Carnwell.
欢迎卡恩威尔先生和夫人。
Please take a seat.
请坐。
Thank you.
谢谢。
So, I understand that your family spending has skyrocketed and you want to start budgeting.
所以，我了解到你们家的支出飙升了，你们想开始做预算。
Yes, that's correct.
是的，没错。
Frankly speaking, our household income is relatively high and we have never had any
坦白说，我们的家庭收入相对较高，从来没有遇到过钱的问题。
money problems.
钱的问题。
But I think this is the main reason as to why our spending has gone out of control.
但我认为这正是我们支出失控的主要原因。
We have two kids and with allowances, paying their credit cards, ours, and not to mention
我们有两个孩子，要付零花钱、还他们的信用卡、我们的信用卡，更不用说房贷和车贷了。
our mortgage and car payments.
房贷和车贷。
With the recent economic downturn, my husband's business has suffered and now we need some
最近经济不景气，我丈夫的生意受到了影响，现在我们需要一些建议，如何制定家庭预算。
advice as how we can prepare a family budget.
家庭预算。
I see.
我明白了。
Well, you have come to the right place.
嗯，你来对地方了。
First, what we need to do is determine your cash flow.
首先，我们需要确定你的现金流。
Knowing how much money is coming in will help us allocate spending to different categories
知道有多少钱进账，能帮助我们分配支出到不同类别，比如房贷、教育、食品杂货等。
such as mortgage, education, groceries, etc.
食品杂货等。
Yes, that makes sense.
是的，有道理。
Secondly, I need you to bring all of your receipts for the last two to three months.
其次，我需要你把过去两到三个月的所有收据都带来。
That way we can determine what your average expenditures are and see which category you
这样我们就能确定你的平均支出，看看你在哪个类别上花钱最多。
are spending money on the most.
花钱最多。
Usually, your fixed costs are higher and we can't do much about that.
通常，你的固定成本较高，我们对此无能为力。
But we can usually trim your variable costs such as entertainment or clothing.
但我们可以削减你的可变成本，比如娱乐或服装。
Great!
太棒了！
We will do that then.
那我们就这么办吧。
Now how about we treat you to a nice dinner?
现在，我们请你吃顿好的晚餐怎么样？
That's another thing.
这是另一回事。
If you really want to stop spending so much money, throw away at least half of your credit
如果你真的想停止花那么多钱，那就扔掉至少一半的信用卡
cards.
吧。
Alright we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now talking about allowances, you said you had an allowance when you were a kid.
那么现在说到零花钱，你说你小时候有零花钱。
Did you really have a $10 a week allowance?
你真的每周有10美元的零花钱吗？
No, I think it was like $8.
不，我想大概是8美元。
It started out at $6 or $5 a week and then I think the most I got was like $10 or $11.
一开始是每周6或5美元，然后我想我拿到最多的就是10或11美元。
So it was like almost about a dollar a day.
所以差不多每天一美元。
About that.
差不多吧。
But usually the point was that, well, I started working when I was 15 because my parents thought
但通常重点是，嗯，我15岁就开始工作了，因为我父母认为
it was important for children to learn how money works.
让孩子了解钱是怎么运作的很重要。
But I was given that money because at the time it was enough money to go out one night.
但我拿到那笔钱是因为当时那笔钱足够出去一晚。
So on Friday nights if I wanted to go out with my friends, I could go out to watch a
所以周五晚上如果我想和朋友出去，我可以去看场
movie and get a slice of pizza and $10 was enough.
电影，再吃块披萨，10美元就够了。
Now $10 doesn't even buy you a ticket to the movie.
现在10美元连一张电影票都买不到。
But at the time it was more than enough.
但当时那是绰绰有余的。
So this is important I guess because different families have different ways of upbringing
所以我想这很重要，因为不同的家庭有不同的方式教育
their children and in many cases this doesn't happen.
孩子，而在很多情况下，这种情况并不发生。
If I want to go out to the movies on a Saturday, then my parents will give me $30.
如果我想周六出去看电影，我父母会给我30美元。
And if I want to go out next weekend, they'll also give me money.
如果我想下个周末出去，他们也会给我钱。
So it's interesting to see the contrast because obviously when I was a kid also I didn't really
所以看到这种对比很有趣，因为显然我小时候也没有
get this opportunity of going out all the time.
经常出去的机会。
And actually I had to work for it.
而且实际上我得为此工作。
So if I wanted to go out on the weekend, I would get an allowance but also I would have
所以如果我想周末出去，我会拿到零花钱，但我也得
to wash the car, that was typical with my dad.
洗车，那是我爸的惯例。
I had to wash the car.
我得洗车。
Well, I think it's interesting because it shows that the parents want to teach their
嗯，我觉得这很有趣，因为这表明父母想教
children about budgeting.
孩子关于预算的知识。
Because if you only have $10, you really have to budget.
因为如果你只有10美元，你真的得精打细算。
You have to decide how you will allocate that money even though it's not very much.
你必须决定如何分配那笔钱，即使它不多。
So in some ways it's good practice.
所以从某些方面来说，这是很好的练习。
Yeah, it is.
是啊，没错。
I think it's done us well.
我觉得这对我们有好处。
We're not in debt.
我们没有负债。
Not yet.
还没有。
All right.
好了。
So let us know how allowances work in your country or maybe did you have an allowance
所以请告诉我们零花钱在你们国家是怎么运作的，或者你小时候
when you were a kid?
有没有零花钱？
A lot of people didn't have an allowance.
很多人没有零花钱。
I know a lot of friends didn't get allowances.
我知道很多朋友都没有零花钱。
So come to our website EnglishPod.com and if you have any other questions or doubts,
所以请访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com，如果你还有其他问题或疑问，
please leave them there as well.
也请留在那里。
We hope to hear from you.
我们期待你的来信。
Until next time.
下次再见。
We'll hit you up and let you know where to find us.
我们会联系你，告诉你我们在哪里。